<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info"
  docName="draft-daley-rswg-limited-mutability-00" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes=""
  updates="2026 8153 9280" submissionType="editorial" xml:lang="en" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Limited Mutability for RFCs">Limited Mutability for RFCs</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-daley-rswg-limited-mutability-00"/>

    <author fullname="Jay Daley" initials="J." surname="Daley">
      <!-- all of the following elements are optional -->
      <organization>IETF Administration LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <street>1000 N West St, Ste 1200</street>
          <city>Wilmington</city>
          <region>Delaware</region>
          <code>19801</code>
          <country>US</country>
          <!-- Uses two letter country code -->
        </postal>
        <email>jay@staff.ietf.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2023"/>
    <!-- On draft subbmission:
         * If only the current year is specified, the current day and month will be used.
         * If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, the current day will
           be used
         * If the year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month and day="1" will be used.
    -->

    <area>RFC Editor</area>
    <workgroup>RFC Series Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>immutability</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>The environment in which RFCs are produced has changed significantly since the inception of
        the series: the process for producing RFCs is now a heavyweight process; there is a large
        and growing set of errata, many with serious implications; and the expectations around the
        use of RFCs have changed significantly as document technology has evolved. In this new
        environment, the long-standing principle of immutability of RFCs, prevents the RFC Series
        from achieving its goals of technical excellence and easily understood documentation. This
        document addresses that by identifying a possible way forward of a new principle of limited
        mutability for the RFC Series that allows the publishing of new versions of RFCs in limited
        circumstances, replacing the principle of immutability.</t>
    </abstract>
    <note removeInRFC="true">
      <name>About This Document</name>
      <t>This document is written by the IETF Executive Director, an employee of the IETF
        Administration LLC, whose role excludes them from having any direct influence on the
        Internet standards process. This document is intended as a discussion document for the RSWG
        about the overall RFC Series, and therefore broader than the Internet standards process,
        though inevitably it will have an influence on the Internet standards process if adopted.
        Given that potential, the IETF Chair has given permission for this author to produce this
        document as a discussion document.</t>
      <t>Status information for this document may be found at <eref
          target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-daley-rswg-limited-mutability/"/>. </t>
      <t> Discussion of this document takes place on the RFC Series Working Group Editorial Stream
        Working Group mailing list (<eref target="mailto:rswg@rfc-editor.org"/>), which is archived
        at <eref target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/browse/rswg/"/>. </t>
      <t>Source for this draft and an issue tracker can be found at <eref
          target="https://github.com/JayDaley/draft-daley-rswg-limited-mutability"/>.</t>
    </note>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <section>
        <name>Principle of Immutability</name>
        <t>The RFC Series has a long established principle of immutability as documented in <xref
            section="2.1" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC2026"/>, <xref section="2.2"
            sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8153"/> and <xref section="7.6" sectionFormat="of"
            target="RFC9280"/>.</t>

        <t>This principle was entirely appropriate when the series first began. The process for
          authoring and publishing an RFC was lightweight and, as those initial RFCs were typed up
          and distributed in hard copy, it was neither practical nor necessary to issue corrected
          versions. Even after RFCs switched to an electronic format, for many years the process for
          authoring and publishing an RFC was sufficiently lightweight that any serious error in an
          RFC could be corrected by publishing a new RFC.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Changed Environment</name>
        <t>The environment around the RFC Series has gradually transitioned and is now very
          different in three key aspects:</t>
        <ol>
          <li><t>For the bulk of RFCs, the process for authoring and publishing is now intentionally
              a heavyweight process. This change began most notably with <xref target="RFC2026"/>
              and continued with many subsequent updates to the process. <xref target="RFC2026"/>
              set out some principles that determined the need for a heavier weight process, two of
              which are particularly relevant here:</t>
            <ul>
              <li>technical excellence;</li>
              <li>clear, concise, and easily understood documentation;</li>
            </ul></li>
          <li>The collection and verification of errata began in 2000, though not formally
            documented in an RFC until RFC 7322 in 2014, and the verification process has been
            refined a number of times since. At the time of writing there are now 2944 verified
            errata, ranging in seriousness from simple spelling errors through to errors in the text
            that completely invert the intended meaning. This is in addition to another 2069
            reported errata that have been identified as suitable for consideration in future
            updates of the document.</li>
          <li>The expectations and technology for managing, distributing and consuming documents,
            and new versions of documents, has evolved significantly. Of particular note to the IETF
            is that there is now an increasing push for all technical documents to become more and
            more like code - computer readable including the semantic structure, and tracked in
            version control systems. The RFC Series has responded directly to this with the switch
            to XML as the canonical source publication format for RFCs, and the extensive use of
            GitHub by authors.</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>The Problems</name>
        <t>The RFC Series now faces a number of problems relating to immutability.</t>
        <t>The first and most serious of these is that there are many published RFCs that are known
          to contain serious errors and are being actively used by implementers and others who are
          entirely unaware of this. While there have been experiments in displaying RFCs with inline
          errata, no serious attempts have been made to ensure that implementers or other consumers
          of RFCs are not misled by these errors. This current position violates the two principles
          from RFC 2026 above - RFCs with known serious errors are neither technically excellent nor
          easily understood.</t>
        <t>The second is that the use of XML as the canonical source format has created a new
          “layer” to the RFCs, the markup layer, that has its own set of issues and opportunities
          including:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>errors in the XML that do not affect the content of the RFC;</li>
          <li>use of XML constructs, features or libraries that become defunct;</li>
          <li>potential for adding new XML markup that enhances the computer readability of an RFC
            without changing the content;</li>
          <li>errors in the published formats of RFCs that are rendered from the canonical source
            XML;</li>
          <li>potential for amending/enhancing the rendered formats.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
          NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown
          here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>New Principle</name>
      <t>The following new principle is presented as a possible way forward to address these
        concerns, while avoiding a radical change to the RFC Series with all the implications of
        such a change.</t>
      <section>
        <name>Limited Mutability</name>
        <t>The new principle for the RFC Series is limited mutability, which replaces the previous
          principle of immutability. This principle is stated as follows:</t>
        <t><em>With limitations, and solely to maintain either the correctness of the content, or
            the utility of the metadata, markup, layout and renderings, of an RFC, a new version of
            an RFC or a new version of an existing rendering, MAY be published, replacing the
            previously published RFC or rendering.</em></t>
        <section>
          <name>Key Definitions</name>
          <t>The key definitions of terms in this principle are as follows:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>A new version of an RFC is defined as a new version of the canonical source, where
              any combination of the content, metadata, markup and layout changes. The nature of the
              canonical source depends on the specific RFC. For example, for some it is an RFCXML
              file, for others a plain text file and for others a plain text transcription of a
              typewritten document.</li>
            <li>A rendering of an RFC is any published format derived from the canonical
              source.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Limitations</name>
          <t>The general limitation of this principle is to restrict publication of new versions to
            the only those absolutely necessary to maintain correctness and utility, which leads to
            the following more detailed limitations:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>Content changes MUST only be the verbatim application of verified errata.</li>
            <li>Publishing new versions of an RFC solely for the application of editorial errata
              SHOULD be avoided. Exceptional circumstances could include a full republication of all
              RFCs, or an RFC with multiple editorial errata such that the quality suffers.</li>
            <li>New versions of an RFC MUST NOT be published for an RFC designated as historic or
              obsolete. New versions of an RFC MAY be published for an RFC whose status is
              unknown.</li>
            <li>New versions of an RFC or new versions of a rendering of an RFC SHOULD NOT be
              published so often that it risks undermining the reputation or utility of the series.
              There may be exceptional circumstances whereby it is agreed that a risk to the
              reputation of the series is acceptable. </li>
            <li>A new version of a rendering of an RFC, where the canonical source of that RFC has
              not changed since the last version of the rendering, MUST NOT have any change in
              content, except to correct a discrepancy in the content between the rendering and the
              canonical source.</li>
            <li>Publishing a new version of an RFC or a new version of a rendering of an RFC where
              nothing changes except the version number, SHOULD be avoided. There may be exceptional
              circumstances where this is necessary.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Correctness and Utility</name>
          <t>Correctness and utility are measured as follows, though more detailed or more
            applicable measures may be developed over time:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>The correctness of content SHOULD be measured against the long-standing Internet
              standards principles of ‘technical excellence’ and ‘easily understood’.</li>
            <li>The utility of metadata, markup, layout and renderings SHOULD be measured against
              the reasonable expectations of implementers, researchers and other common consumers of
              RFCs, and the IETF community and RFC Editor function as producers of RFCs.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Additional Notes</name>
          <t>The following notes are provided to explain certain choices in the development of this
            principle.</t>
          <t>A specific minimum time period between publications is intentionally not provided as
            this may change as expectations of RFC consumers change, and because it would need to be
            different for different renderings. For example, the HTML or HTML-ised rendering of an
            RFC could change much more frequently than the PDF rendering while still meeting the
            limitations above.</t>
          <t>Under this policy, when one RFC updates another that cannot result in a content change
            in the updated RFC. Updates do not always specify the precise text to change and even
            when they do, they rarely provide a clear statement of the new text. It would therefore
            require an entirely new process to determine the exact text to change, which is out of
            scope for this document.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Further Considerations</name>
      <section>
        <name>Operational Implementation</name>
        <t>This document intentionally leave several implementation details unspecified as these are
          best considered operational matters for the RFC Editor to determine:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Version naming scheme;</li>
          <li>Document name resolution;</li>
          <li>Archival process and archive access requirements;</li>
          <li>New version notification and distribution process.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Potential Implications</name>
        <t>Adoption of this new principle could to lead to the following:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>There is likely to be an impact on the policies and processes of third-party
            organisations that archive the RFC Series.</li>
          <li>The volume of errata reports and therefore the associated processing effort, is likely
            to drop as it will be much less likely that someone reports an error that has already
            been corrected.</li>
          <li>Authors may be more likely to add less stable references than they do now, with the
            expectation that these can be replaced if they break.</li>
          <li>There could be more scrutiny on the errata verification process and more concerns
            about community oversight, which may lead to a need for the process to be reviewed.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Updates</name>
      <t>If this principle were adopted then that would mean updating <xref section="2.1"
          sectionFormat="parens" target="RFC2026"/>, <xref section="2.2" sectionFormat="parens"
          target="RFC8153"/> and <xref section="7.6" sectionFormat="parens" target="RFC9280"/> to
        note that RFCs are now mutable in limited circumstances.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The implementation of the new principle identified in this document would enhance the
        security of the Internet by reducing the number of occasions when an implementer is
        presented with an RFC with serious errors in it.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8153.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9280.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>This document was only possible after many conversations with Alexis Rossi, Alice Russo,
        Jean Mahoney. John Levine, Martin Thomson, Paul Hoffman, Robert Sparks and Sandy Ginoza, and
        email exchanges with Steve Crocker and Scott Bradner.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
